Finding Aid for Greg Kamm papers, 1963-2008
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Greg Kamm papers 1963-2008
Kamm, Greg
1 oversize folders
7 linear feet
2009188 Aa2 UAm
Student activist who was involved with SDS, co-founded Kalamazoo Gay Liberation at Western Michigan University in 1970, and was involved with the Gay Liberation Movement at Michigan State University in the early 1970s. Greg Kamm later became an ESL teacher and served in the Peace Corps before teaching English in Thailand, South Korea, and Saudi Arabia. Collection includes photographs, personal journals, and papers documenting Kamm’s involvement with various organizations.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by the estate of Gregory C. Kamm (donor no. 10240 ) in August 2009.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is closed to research until January 1, 2034.
Gregory Curtis Kamm, the only child of Jack and Maxine Kamm, was born October 15, 1950 in Muskegon, MI. He attended Muskegon Catholic Central High School and there began a life-long attachment to Catholicism that was interrupted by deep spiritual doubts and questions during undergraduate and graduate studies. Michigan State University declined to accept Kamm upon his high school graduation and he instead entered Western Michigan University where he soon became involved with the New Left movement. He attended SDS meetings, contributed to the Western Activist (a publication produced by the group Students for Social Involvement (SSI)), and helped organize a large takeover of the WMU student center.
After being detained and referred to school authorities for his role in the student center events, Kamm's activism became focused on his involvement with the burgeoning Gay Rights movement. He helped co-found Kalamazoo Gay Liberation, the first known Gay Rights group in the city, and was an officer in Michigan State University's Gay Liberation Movement (GLM) after being admitted to graduate school. During his tenure at MSU, GLM solidified its place in history by helping to pass a progressive anti-discrimination ordinance in East Lansing.
After spending the summer of 1973 in New York City, Kamm grew disillusioned with elements in the Gay Rights movement and gradually cut off his affiliation with the Gay Liberation Movement and related organizations. He taught English as a Second Language (ESL) through the 1970's and early 80's and traveled widely; these two activities would remain constants for the remainder of his life. In 1985, Kamm began a stint with the Peace Corps and then worked as an ESL instructor in Thailand, South Korea, and Saudi Arabia. In between positions, he toured Southeast Asia, India, and Africa; served as a formal observer in free elections in Mozambique, South Africa, and Cambodia; and worked for UNESCO in Laos.
Greg Kamm died on June 3, 2008 in Saudi Arabia (where he was working at the time) after being hospitalized for several months due to complications from Hepatitis A contracted while he was on vacation in India in December 2007.
Due to his involvement with SDS in the late 1960's and the Gay Rights movement in the early 70's, the Greg Kamm papers are a highly valuable resource for scholars and citizens interested in the history of student activism in Michigan. The papers are especially important for understanding the evolution of Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender rights in the state because Kamm, as cofounder of Kalamazoo Gay Liberation and an officer of the Gay Liberation Movement at MSU, was intimately involved with the movement in the years immediately succeeding the Stonewall riots. At the same time, materials related to Kamm's experiences abroad as a traveler and ESL teacher offer a Michigander's view of the world and his 31 years' worth of journals provide a fascinating insight into Kamm's transitions from activism to eastern philosophy and, ultimately, to the consolation of his early Catholicism. The Greg Kamm papers are divided into four series: Biographical Materials, Student Activism, Visual Materials, and Journals.
Subjects:
Election monitoring.; Gay rights--Michigan.; Gay Liberation Movement (East Lansing, Mich.); Kalamazoo Gay Liberation.; Kamm, Greg, 1950-2008.; Students--Political activity.; Students for a Democratic Society (U.S.); Alternative publications--Michigan.; English teachers.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Election monitoring--Mozambique--1994.; Election monitoring--South Africa--1994.; Gay Liberation Movement (East Lansing, Mich.); Gay rights--Michigan.; Kalamazoo Gay Liberation.; Kamm, Greg, 1950-2008.; Student movements.; Teaching--South Korea.; Teaching--Thailand.; Travel.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Biographical Materials
  The Biographical Materials series documents aspects of Kamm's personal life and contains correspondence, educational materials, writings, and other documents.
  - Correspondence
    - Harbeson, T.E. 1971-1974 (Box 1)
    - Other 1971-1978 (Box 1)
  - Cutler (Louise) obituaries 1971 (Box 1)
    (Kamm's maternal grandmother)
  - Drawings and sketches
    - Portrait of Gregory C. Kamm 1979 (Folder 1)
    - Other undated (Box 1)
      (artists unknown)
  - Education
    - Muskegon Catholic Central High School
      - Clippings 1967 (Box 1)
      - Coursework and essays 1965-1968 (Box 1)
    - Western Michigan University (WMU)
      - Coursework and essays
        - "Homosexuality and the Illegitimate Power Structure" 1971 (Box 1)
        - Various 1968-1970 (Box 1)
      - Official correspondence 1969 (Box 1)
    - Michigan State University
      - Coursework and essays
        - "Gay Subculture and its Language" 1972 (Box 1)
        - Various 1972-1976 (Box 1)
      - Official correspondence 1968, 1971 (Box 1)
      - Transcript 1972 (Box 1)
    - Theology coursework and essays 1980-1983 (Box 1)
      (school unspecified)
  - Oral History Interview (MI Gay, Lesbian, Bisexual and Transgender Life) correspondence and consent form 2005 (Box 1)
  - Teachers of English to Speakers of Other Languages (TESOL) materials 1983-1984 (Box 1)
  - Writings
    - "Oral inactivity (or, How I Lived with Fags and Lived to Tell about It)" circa 1970 (Box 1)
    - "A Pieta Tale" circa 1990s, includes copies of the novella on 3.25" floppy disks (Box 1)
    - Various creative pieces circa 1970 (Box 1)
    - Various nonfiction, undated 1971 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous circa 1960s-2003 (Box 1)
- Student Activism
  The Student Activism series documents Kamm's personal involvement in (as well as the larger context of) activist student groups in the late 60's and early 70's. The series is divided into two subseries, New Left and progressive student movements and Gay Rights movement. The former details Kamm's involvement with SDS and other groups (including the Free Underground Committee of Kalamazoo) at Western Michigan University includes flyers, tracts, publications, and clippings related to various issues and events. The latter subseries documents Kamm's leadership in Kalamazoo Gay Liberation and MSU's Gay Liberation Movement and includes meeting minutes, organizational records, and clippings. In both subseries, the clippings contain some articles and opinion pieces written by Kamm.
  - The New Left and progressive student movements
    - Personal and organizational materials
      - Personal correspondence 1969 (Box 1)
      - Article manuscript (by Greg Kamm) on student unrest at Western Michigan University 1969 (Box 1)
      - Western Michigan University Men's Disciplinary Board hearing (for Greg Kamm) 1969 (Box 1)
      - Draft resistance and conscientious objector materials circa 1969 (Box 1)
      - The Free Underground Committee of Kalamazoo 1969 (Box 1)
      - The Liberation News Front 1969 (Box 1)
      - Students for a Democratic Society (SDS) circa 1968-1972 (Box 1)
        (includes materials from SDS groups in Muskegon, Western Michigan University, Kalamazoo, and Michigan State University)
      - Various student activist flyers, statements, and events at Western Michigan University circa 1968-1969 (Box 1)
    - Collected publications and clippings (includes some articles and opinion pieces written by Greg Kamm)
      - Black & Red (Kalamazoo), circa 1969 (Box 1)
      - The Catholic Worker (New York), 1968 (Box 1)
      - Kalamazoo Gazette, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
      - Kalamazoo Proper, circa 1969 (Box 1)
        (first issue; introduced after the closure of the Western Activist)
      - Movement (San Francisco), 1968 (Box 1)
      - Muskegon Chronicle, 1963-1969 (Box 1)
      - Radical Education Project (Ann Arbor): literature lists circa 1969 (Box 1)
      - SDS
        - New Left Notes (Chicago), 1968-1969 (Box 1)
        - Various publications circa 1960s (Box 1)
      - Western Activist (Kalamazoo), circa 1968-1969 (Box 1)
      - Western Herald (WMU student paper), 1968-1969, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Other undated (Box 1)
        (article by Greg Kamm in an unidentified newspaper)
  - Gay Rights movement
    - Kalamazoo Gay Liberation (organization co-founded by Greg Kamm at Western Michigan University)
      - Correspondence 1971 (Box 1)
      - Discussion of organizational purpose and significance 1971 (Box 1)
      - Guidelines (Kalamazoo Gay Liberation purpose and goals) 1970 (Box 1)
      - Organizational history circa 1971 (Box 1)
      - "The Kalamazoo Boys in the Band" theatrical production
        - Event Program 1970 (Box 1)
        - Review (written by Greg Kamm) 1970 (Box 1)
    - Gay Liberation Movement (organization Greg Kamm helped lead while at Michigan State University)
      - Anti-sex law manifesto (attributed to Radical Gay Alliance, Gays for Motherhood and Apple Pie, and the Gay Revolutionary Party) circa 1972 (Box 1)
      - Application for "Do A Fool" Weekend in Detroit (sponsored by the Tribe) 1972 (Box 1)
      - Clippings 1972-1973 (Box 1)
        (includes some articles and opinion pieces written by Greg Kamm)
      - Correspondence 1972, 1979 (Box 1)
      - East Lansing sex bias hearings and ordinance clippings and materials 1972 (Box 1)
      - Gay Pride Week 1972
        - Photographs copied by Greg Kamm for MI Gay, Lesbian, Bisexual and Transgender Life (Box 1)
        - Song Sheet (Box 1)
      - Meeting minutes and materials related to Gay Liberation Movement activities 1972-1973 (Box 1)
        (originally housed in a binder)
      - Statement of purpose 1972 (Box 1)
      - Sunflower ("Lansing's Gay Newspaper"), circa 1972 (Box 1)
        (includes an opinion piece written by Greg Kamm)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials series contains both photographs and slides and it covers Kamm's involvement with student groups at WMU and MSU as well as his later travel and teaching activities. The albums from 1969-1973 are of particular interest in that these document a large number of events including the 1972 Detroit Gay Pride Parade and associated Gay Pride Week events as well as other Gay Liberation Movement activities. The travel and teaching photographs track Kamm's movements through Europe, Egypt, Bahrain, India, Nepal, Thailand, Vietnam, Cambodia, Laos, South Korea, Saudi Arabia and elsewhere. Photographs also document Kamm's family and close friends, including fellow teacher Donna Clark, and his participation as an elections monitor in South Africa and Mozambique.
  - Photographs
    - Albums: friends, family, and events
      - 1969 (Box 1)
      - 1969-1971 (Box 1)
        (includes images from Kalamazoo Gay Liberation events)
      - March 1971-August 1971 (Box 2)
      - December 1971-June 1972 (Box 2)
        (includes images from Gay Liberation Movement events)
      - June 1972 (Box 2)
        (includes images from the Gay Liberation Movement's celebration of Gay Pride Week 1972)
      - October 1972-April 1973 (Box 2)
      - June 1973-August 1973 (Box 2)
      - August 1973-May 1974 (Box 2)
      - June 1974-December 1974 (Box 2)
    - Election monitoring
      - Mozambique 1994 (Box 2)
      - South Africa 1994 (Box 2)
    - Harbeson, Thomas E. circa 1970 (Box 3)
    - India vacation 2007 (Box 3)
      (trip on which Kamm contracted an ultimately fatal case of Hepatitis A)
    - Kamm (Greg)
      - Family 1972 (Box 3)
      - High school portraits circa 1967 (Box 3)
      - Portraits, 1975- circa 1980s (Box 3)
    - Laos and Cambodia 1971 (Box 3)
    - Muskegon, MI street car riots 1919 (Box 3)
      (reprints)
    - Thai Buddhist monk undated (Box 3)
    - Tibetan Buddhist images circa 1959, 1983 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous: teaching, travel and friends 1969-2007 (Box 3)
      (folders 1-4)
    - Miscellaneous: teaching, travel and friends 1969-2007 (Box 4)
      (folders 5-6)
  - Slides
    - Kamm (Greg) and friends 1972 (Box 4)
    - Laos (from Linda Durnbaugh) 1969-1971, 3 folders (Box 4)
      (folder 1 includes slides from Dan Linger, 1971)
- Journals
  The Journals series contains Kamm's personal diary and records his thoughts, impressions, and activities for every day between 1969 and 2008. As such, the journals provide important information regarding Kamm's work for Gay Rights and the New Left movement and offer a candid portrait of a liberated gay man's experiences, opportunities, and adversities.
  - 1969 (Box 4)
  - 1970 (Box 4)
  - 1971 (Box 4)
  - 1972 (Box 4)
  - 1973 (Box 5)
  - 1974 (Box 5)
  - 1975 (Box 5)
  - 1976 (Box 5)
  - 1977 (Box 5)
  - 1978 (Box 5)
  - 1979 (Box 5)
  - 1980 (Box 5)
  - 1981 (Box 5)
  - 1982 (Box 5)
  - 1983 (Box 5)
  - 1984 (Box 5)
  - 1985 (Box 5)
  - 1986 (Box 6)
  - 1987 (Box 6)
  - 1988 (Box 6)
  - 1989 (Box 6)
  - 1990 (Box 6)
  - 1991 (Box 6)
  - 1992 (Box 6)
  - 1993 (Box 6)
  - 1994 (Box 6)
  - 1995 (Box 6)
  - 1996 (Box 6)
  - 1997 (Box 6)
  - 1998 (Box 7)
  - 1999 (Box 7)
  - 2000 (Box 7)
  - 2001 (Box 7)
  - 2002 (Box 7)
  - 2003 (Box 7)
  - 2004 (Box 7)
  - 2005 (Box 7)
  - 2006 (Box 7)
  - 2007 (Box 7)
  - 2008 (Box 7)